Translator
字 幕 入 力
ssnake
ssnake
Ignorance and nonsense,
無知で無意味
Timing
字 幕 編 集
zwc1991
zwc1991
you are even inferior to dust in this world of sand...
この世界の塵にすら劣る者…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
So you are, you sinners of Fallaina!
それが　お前たちファレナの罪人だ
Masoo, are you OK?
マソオさん！大丈夫？
I'm fine...
大丈夫だ…
Wheeze... Wheeze...
ハア…ハア…
I didn't know...
まったく…
It's getting worsen this fast...
こんなに進行早いのかよ…
Chakuro, do your best.
チャクロたち　頑張ってくれ
Everyone has already reached their limit here...
そろそろみんな限界だぜ…
Hey, you old guy! You will be shot!
おい　おっさん！　狙われるぞ！
Masoo, it's dangerous!
マソオさん　危ないよ
Kuchiba!
クチバ！
That person has been living for somebody for her whole life...
…あの人はずっと誰かの為に生きてきた
In order to make us people on the island happy,
この島の民たちが幸せでいられるように
she sacrificed herself and was always standing by us.
自分を犠牲にして皆に幸せを与え続けてきた
Do you guys know the weight of her life?
その人生の重みが分かるか
She is not somebody...
お前らなんかに…
She is not somebody that you can take her life that easily!
お前らなんかに命を奪われていい人ではなかった…！
What the hell are you doing there, you scrawny idiot shit!
なにやってんだ　このくそ馬鹿モヤシが！
S... Scrawny idiot shit!?
く、くそ馬鹿モヤシ…？
Don't get in my way!
じゃ、邪魔をするな！
You don't wanna die in vain right, you old guy!
無駄死にしてえのか　おっさん！
Nonsense!
うるさい…！
It's not nonsense!
うるさくねえ！
sentikinesis
サイミア
You don't even able to use thymia!
情念動も使えないくせに！
What the heck?
なんだと！
Ugly.
みにくい
You are ugly.
みにくいな
People with emotions,
感情を残した人間は
are always full of hatred and anger.
いつも憎しみと怒りでいっぱいだ
You are really ugly.
じつにみにくい
Ugly is not our fault.
醜くて何が悪い
And also...
だが…
You guys who hide your faces and kill others have no right to say that to us!
素顔を隠して人を殺す連中に言われる筋合いは無い！
A child...
子供だ…
What's up?
どうした
Can't you kill me?
ころせないのか？
I will revenge Taisha-sama for you.
タイシャ様の仇は討ってやる
That's... enough...
もう…　やめてくれ…
Don't do so...
頼む
...I wonder
…俺の娘
if my daughter was still alive, how she would be.
生きてたらどんな風になってたのかねえ
παγώνι
παγώνι
Pagóni.
パゴニ
Oni!
オウニ！
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
δαίμονας
デモナス
The Daímonas of Fallaina...
ファレナの悪霊…
After all it's a superstition... So boring.
所詮は迷信か　つまらん
Give that to me!
貸せ
The livings inferior to the dusts in the sea of sand,
砂上の塵にすら劣る存在
you ought to disappear!
消えるがいい
Of cuz, we know that!
分かってんだよ！んなことぐらい！
We were closed in a narrow island,
ちっせえ島に閉じ込められて…
and we know nothing about the world!
セカイの何も知らねえ！
We can influence nothing!
なんにも影響できねえ！
That's what we are!
それが俺たちだってな！
I will get you out of that mud ship!
あんな泥船なんか出てってやる！
So! Fuck off you dude!
だから！　邪魔すんじゃねえ
You baldy!
このハゲ！
Oni!
オウニ！
You guys can never stop us!
てめえらなんかに止められねえよ！
We are
俺たちが
the internal moles!
「体内モグラ」だ！
Bring it on!
かかってこいよ！
Whenever Oni and I are together,
俺とオウニがいっしょなら
we are the strongest!
いつだって最強なんだよ！
Never mock us again!
二度と俺たちをバカにするんじゃねえ
Oni!
オウニ！
Are you OK, Oni...
大丈夫か　オウニ…
Don't waste my time with those mice.
ネズミ相手に何をもたついている
Kill them as soon as possible!
さっさと始末しろ
We have... always... been...
ずっ…と…いっしょ
together...
だったんだ…
O...
オウ…
Nibi?
ニビ…？
I'll bring you to the world outside!
俺が外の世界に連れてってやる！
How can thymia be used?
サイミアだと？
Why... It's impossible!
なぜだ…ありえない
νοῦς
νοῦς
αὔρα
アウラ
How can aura appears at the room of Nous
「ヌースの間」で　念紋が…
Oni! Nibi!
オウニ！　ニビ！
Chakuro, dangerous!
チャクロ　危ない！
δαίμονας
δαίμονας
Daímonas...
デモナス…
Lykos!
リコス！
Chakuro!
チャクロ！
How... How can it be happened...
こ…こんなこと　あってはならない…
I see...! It's because we broke a taboo!
そうだ…！禁忌など犯したから…！
όρκα
όρκα
Orca's idea made it happen!
オルカの策が招いたのだ！
δαίμονας
δαίμονας
He waked up the Daímonas...! Caused by his...
デモナスを呼び覚ました…！あいつの…！
Hey, Shaggy! What happened?
おい　モジャモジャ！　どーなってるんだコレ？
I dunno!
分かんねえよ！
Chakky...
チャッキー…
Lykos!
リコス！
Lykos! Are you OK?
リコス！大丈夫？
Oni! Oni! Where are you?
オウニ！オウニ　どこ？
Nibi!
ニビ…！
I was asking you don't leave me alone,
置いてかないでくれって思ってたけど
but... it turned out to be I left you alone.
なんか…逆になっちまったな
Nibi...
ニビ…
Sorry, but you can't.
ごめん…ダメなんだ
You can't take this ship.
この船には乗せられない…
Buki... Aijiro...
ブキ…アイジロ…
How can I say...
なんか…
It's strange.
変な感じ
Don't you...
そんな顔…
feel embarrassed with that face?
照れくさいじゃん
It's the first time I see you cry.
オウニが泣いてるの　初めて見た
Nibi...
ニビ…
Nibi!
ニビッ…！
Listen.
…あのさ
Perhaps you thought... if we can't help you get out of the mud whale,
オウニは　泥クジラを出られなきゃ　俺たちに意味なんかない…てさ
we are nonsense.
そう思ってたかもしれないけど…
But indeed... I...
俺…ホントはさ…
Rather than you may thought... that...
お前が思ってる以上に…その…
I was satisfied with my life.
満足してたっていうか…
While I'm longing for the world outside,
外の世界に憧れながら　あの島で…
I would just love to see the changeless sky and sea everyday, with you.
お前と毎日　同じ空と海を見てさ
And that's enough.
…それだけで
That was awesome!
最高だった！
No...
違う…
It's me who was nonsense.
意味が無かったのは…俺だ
If I didn't meet you guys...
あいつらと出会わなければ…
If I didn't be together with you...
ニビと一緒にいなければ…
I have no reason to be there!
俺がここにいていい理由なんて生まれなかった！
Oni...
…オウニ
I'm right here, waiting for you.
いつまでも　待ってるからな
Please show us!
見せてくれ
Please dust the world down, and show us the future!
砂塵を払って　この世界の先を
Nibi...
ニビ…
Nibi!
ニビ…！
Nibi!!
ニビィ！
Oni!
オウニ！
Hey.
…やあ
ολιβίνης
ολιβίνης
My name's Olivines.
ぼくはオリヴィニス
Oli...vines?
…オリ、ヴィニス…？
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
The recorder of Fallaina, let's make a deal!
ファレナの記録者くん　とりひきをしよう
Please devote all the emotions of the people...
君たちの島の人間の感情を
νοῦς
νοῦς
άνθρωπος
άνθρωπος
on your island to the great Anthropos the Nous.
偉大なるヌース･アンスロポスにすべて捧げると
If you can promise that,
そう君が約束してくれたら
άνθρωπος
άνθρωπος
κόκαλο
コカロ
I will give you the bone of Anthropos.
このアンスロポスの骨をあげよう
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
αίμα
エマ
You already have Blood with Fallaina.
ファレナには血がいる
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
αίμα
αίμα
If you can have both Kókkalo and Emma,
コカロとエマが揃えば
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
then Fallaina can get to a new stage.
ファレナは新しいステージへゆくことができる
I don't really understand.
…俺にはよく分からない
But I know I'll have to bring Lykos and Oni back to the mud whale.
リコスやオウニと泥クジラへ戻らなきゃ
What is it?
なんだ？
Chakuro, is it pain?
チャクロ　痛い？
We feel pain
私たちが痛いって感じるのは
because our brains feel pain.
私たちの「アタマ」が痛いって感じてるから
We are shaken and bruised by the pain,
みんなその痛みに振り回されて　傷ついて
and that's why we make mistakes.
過ちを犯すの
Right there.
そこで　だ
If we can tweak the pain and get rid of it.
その痛みを　少ぉしいじって無くしてみよう
It's that easy!
簡単だよ
We just falsify the records of hearts.
「心の記録の改ざん」だ
If we can share the fragments of happiness that the Nous ate from other people,
ヌースが吸い込んだ　様々な人の感情の　幸福な断片だけを
and make it as if our own memory?
まるで　自分のことのように共有できたとしたら…？
Hey, this way!
ほら　こっち！
How was it?
どうだい？
Was the emotion just like your own?
この感情はまるで　君のものだったかのようだろう？
Lykos!
リコス！
How was it?
…どうだい？
You are able to get immersed
すべてが満ち足りた　この世界に
in a world everyone can be satisfied.
ずぅっと浸っていられるよ？
Look.
ほら…
The children of the whale, whose lives were that hard...
今まで辛かったねクジラの子たち…
νοῦς
νοῦς
Let's rewrite your sorry stories with the power of Nous!
君たちの悲しい物語は　ヌースの力で書き換えてしまおう
Rewrite... the painful records?
…辛い記録を…書き換える？
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
The sinners of the whale...
ファレナの罪人たち…
I want to relieve you.
僕は君たちを救済したいんだよ
But...
じゃあ…
But how will our yearnings be?
じゃあ　みんなの想いはどうなるの？
Where will they go?
どこへ行くの？
We have lost Sami, Taisha-sama, Nibi and others.
サミや　タイシャさまや　ニビたちはもういない…
But...
けれど…
They have been with us, right here.
みんなが俺たちと　ここにいた
This is the proves of their lives!
それこそが　みんなの生きた証なんだ
We can never forget them.
忘れるなんて　できない
Even the pains and bitter experiences
痛みや苦しみすべてが
are the records of our lives.
俺たちの生きてきた記録だから
Why... you give me this?
これ…なぜくれるの？
I can't keep that promise!
君との約束は守れないよ？
It's fine.
いいんだ
Because I want to watch the future of your choice.
君の選択のその先が見たい
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Proceed, the sinners of the whale!
進めよ　ファレナの罪人たち
Getting to the new world!
新しい世界へ…！
Let's go, Lykos!
行こう…！リコス…！
July 17, 93 S.S.
砂刑暦93年　7月17日
The sandstorm since the morning had finally begun to calm in the evening.
朝から続いた砂嵐は　夕刻には凪ぎ始めた
σκύλος
σκύλος
When we were trying to escape from the Skulax,
私たちがスキロスから脱出を図ろうとしていた時
contrary to the collapsing ship,
崩壊していく　あの船の様子とは対照的に
the sea was so calm.
風は穏やかだった
It was really painful to leave the died fellow there.
死んでしまった仲間たちを置いていくのは
However, we kept them in our minds,
だが　彼らの想いを胸に刻み
promised we will never forget them,
決して忘れないと誓いを立てて
and then we left.
その場を後にした
Though we were not used to fighting,
戦うことに慣れていなかった私たちは
we took up the weapons and resisted our destiny with our own will.
自らの意志で武器を取り　運命に抗った
There was no other way
戦うことでしか
except fighting if we wanted to protect our paradise.
私たちの楽園を守ることは　できなかった
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
Many friends died, and returned to the sea of sand.
多くの仲間が死に　砂の海へと還っていった
For me, I wanted to write down all these happenings,
私は　そのすべてを書き残すことで
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
in order to have proves of their lives.
彼らが生きた証を残してあげたかった
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
This is, the responsibility and the meaning of me,
それが　生き残った私の
as a survival, and as a recorder.
記録者としての　在るべき意味だった
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
虫の唄
虫の唄
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう